<doc>
    <docno>
     NYT19981231.0011
    </docno>
    <doctype>
     NEWS STORY
    </doctype>
    <date_time>
     1998-12-31 00:48
    </date_time>
    <header>
     A3003 ttc-z r a BC-STOLEN-ID-LADN 12-31 0490
    </header>
    <slug>
     BC-STOLEN-ID-LADN
    </slug>
    <headline>
     LOS ANGELES COUNTY DA TARGETS IDENTITY THEFT
    </headline>
    (For use by NYTimes News Service clients) (Also moving in the ``n'' California news file.) BY PETER HARTLAUB c.1998 Los Angeles Daily News
    <text>
     <p>
      LOS ANGELES _ For the last two years, Mari Frank has spent more than 500 hours and $10,000 to clear her name because a Ventura, Calif., woman assumed her identity, stole her credit record and racked up debt along the way.
     </p>
     <p>
      ``She got a red convertible Mustang in my name. ... I think she's still driving it,'' Frank said.
     </p>
     <p>
      Prosecutors said Frank was the victim of the fastest-growing crime in America: identity theft.
     </p>
     <p>
      Starting on Friday, California will become only the ninth state to prosecute identity theft as a felony. The new law is the latest in a series of recent local and federal guidelines set up to protect Americans from the misappropriation of a name, Social Security number, driver's license or any other form of identification for monetary gain.
     </p>
     <p>
      The Secret Service estimates that identity theft cost U.S. citizens $750 million last year, up from $450 million in 1996.
     </p>
     <p>
      ``Identity theft is the fastest-growing crime in America, maybe even the world,'' Los Angeles County District Attorney Gil Garcetti said at a news conference Wednesday to explain the new law.
     </p>
     <p>
      Penalties will include prison sentences of up to three years and fines up to $10,000.
     </p>
     <p>
      Until a year ago, there was no legal punishment in California for identity theft. In January, it became a misdemeanor, infrequently prosecuted by most district attorneys' offices in the state.
     </p>
     <p>
      In July, a new civil law became effective, forcing credit agencies to clear the records of identity-theft victims who can present a police report documenting the fraud.
     </p>
     <p>
      Garcetti said the law will give his prosecutors the ammunition they need to fight identity theft.
     </p>
     <p>
      Identity theft also became a federal felony this year, punishable by up to 15 years in prison.
     </p>
     <p>
      Officials said increased use of computers, along with the ease of getting a credit card by mail, is responsible for the rise in identity crimes. But an identity thief doesn't need to be a master hacker to get sensitive information.
     </p>
     <p>
      Frank, who suggests people shred discarded mail, said some criminals find personal identity information in a trash bin.
     </p>
     <p>
      Frank said her alter ego, who was prosecuted under credit card fraud laws and sentenced to a work furlough program, got the credit information from a computer database that private investigators use. Within a few months, the identity thief had obtained checks, a driver's license and even business cards in Frank's name.
     </p>
     <p>
      After Frank found out about the crime, the Laguna Niguel, Calif., lawyer spent hundreds of hours talking on the phone and writing letters before her record was clean.
     </p>
     <p>
      ``I am the true, real Mari Frank and it was not very easy to prove that,'' she said.
     </p>
    </text>
    <trailer>
     NYT-12-31-98 0048EST
    </trailer>
   </doc>
   