<doc>
    <docno>
     NYT19990913.0348
    </docno>
    <doctype>
     NEWS STORY
    </doctype>
    <date_time>
     1999-09-13 19:54
    </date_time>
    <header>
     A0745 tta-z u a BC-HURRICANE-FLOYD-ART-5 09-13 1200
    </header>
    <slug>
     BC-HURRICANE-FLOYD-ART-560nADD-NYT
    </slug>
    <headline>
     FLORIDA BRACES AS MASSIVE STORM MOVES TOWARD COAST
    </headline>
    (ATTN: Fla.) (ART ADV: Photo is being sent to NYT photo clients. A map is being sent to NYT graphic clients. Non-subscribers can make individual purchase by calling 888-603-1036 or 888-346-9867.) (js) By RICK BRAGG c.1999 N.Y. Times News Service
    <text>
     <p>
      MIAMI _ A hurricane that meteorologists said was four times the size of the infamous Andrew and potentially even more destructive pounded toward Florida Monday, forcing hundreds of thousands from their homes and leaving countless residents to hope that the massive storm would somehow miss their cities.
     </p>
     <p>
      ``This hurricane,'' said Jerry Jarrell, director of the National Hurricane Center, ``could be catastrophic.''
     </p>
     <p>
      From as far south as Miami to as far north as Cape Canaveral, hundreds of thousands of people evacuated the densely populated Florida coast as the storm, with winds of more than 155 mph, crept westward across the Atlantic and forecasters' radar screens.
     </p>
     <p>
      ``It looks like a giant bullseye out there,'' said Brad Cramer, a lifeguard on Palm Beach.
     </p>
     <p>
      All day Monday, state meteorologists offered hope that Hurricane Floyd would be nudged from its westerly course by a trough of low pressure air moving to the east and southeast, and, instead of making landfall in South Florida, travel up the coast, its dangerous eye offshore.
     </p>
     <p>
      But that hope seemed to weaken by early Monday evening as Floyd plowed west and slightly northwest, in the general direction of Palm Beach.
     </p>
     <p>
      ``This is the sort of the thing you have nightmares about,'' said Bill Bill O'Brien, director of emergency management in Palm Beach County.
     </p>
     <p>
      In a frightening scenario, the hurricane could turn north just as the most powerful winds surrounding the eye make landfall, sending the most destructive part of the hurricane along the coast, meteorologists said.
     </p>
     <p>
      Like Andrew in 1992, which killed 40 people, wrecked 160 homes and caused more than $25 billion in damages, Floyd was a category 4 storm on Monday. It was on the verge of being a category 5, the most powerful, as of Monday evening, with the power to turn houses into rubble and splinters if it makes landfall.
     </p>
     <p>
      But Jarrell warned that even if the hurricane's eye stays as much as 30 miles off the coast the storm could still rip roofs off houses and flatten walls. Meteorologists called it a history-making storm.
     </p>
     <p>
      Jonathan Gottschalck, a research associate in Meteorology at the University of Miami's Rosentiel School of Marine and Atmospheric Science, called it ``one of the largest and strongest storms'' in history to hit the U.S. coast.
     </p>
     <p>
      ``It runs 700 miles in all directions,'' he said of the storm's size, noting that the hurricane-force winds extend 120 miles from its eye. ``We are going to feel it,'' he said.
     </p>
     <p>
      Forecasters, while warning that this hurricane was large and powerful enough to overcome steering winds like the much-hoped-for southeasterly front, still held some hope that the trough would nudge it northeasterly.
     </p>
     <p>
      As night fell on South Florida, shelters and hotel rooms inland, especially around Palm Beach, began to cruise ships left for safer waters to the long flotillas of pleasure craft snaked along canals looking for safe harbor, as lines grew at hardware and grocery stores.
     </p>
     <p>
      Because it was still too soon to more accurately estimate the storm's landfall, the entire state of Florida was placed under a hurricane warning. More than 200,000 people on Florida's east-central coast were told to evacuate, and another 200,000 were evacuated from coastal areas of Miami-Dade County.
     </p>
     <annotation>
      (STORY CAN END HERE. OPTIONAL MATERIAL FOLLOWS)
     </annotation>
     <p>
      Allen Fiske's boat is his home, and he was worried about losing it as the storm drew closer. A paraplegic since a car accident 17 years ago, he lives aboard his 35-foot sailboat, ``Minimum Balance.''
     </p>
     <p>
      ``I don't know what I'm going to do,'' he said. ``I can leave it here at Dinner Key marina and let it get smashed into the pilings, or I could take it up the Miami River along with everybody else and let it get smashed against all the other boats. `I'm leaning toward going south, down to Key Largo.'' The Keys, he said, seem to be the one place in Florida that are out of harm's way.
     </p>
     <p>
      While a few people said they thought the evacuations were premature and a sign of media-driven panic, most people took the threat seriously.
     </p>
     <p>
      ``There have only been two other category 5 hurricanes to hit the U.S. _ Camille in the 1960s and an unnamed storm in 1935,'' said Gottschalck. ``This kind of storm needs to be taken seriously.''
     </p>
     <p>
      As far north as Jacksonville, people watched in amazement as the huge storm swirled across television screens, larger than the state it was approaching.
     </p>
     <p>
      ``Oh, my God,'' said Courtney Edwards, 17, as she saw maps of the storm on a big-screen television in the electronics department of a department store in Jacksonville.
     </p>
     <p>
      Further south, even people who lived miles inland considered leaving their homes.
     </p>
     <p>
      ``We did consider driving to Atlanta,'' said Bettye Cox, who lives in Boca Raton. Instead, she just bought hurricane supplies.
     </p>
     <p>
      As the storm approached, the weather along the South Florida beaches as far north as Palm Beach was balmy and breezy _ a perfect day.
     </p>
     <p>
      Arturo Penalver, 65, a retired longshoreman from Brooklyn, took a swim on Palm Beach. ``It's beautiful,'' said Penalver. ``I don't believe it will come here.''
     </p>
     <p>
      Edmond Zion, a retired limo driver from Queens, also scoffed at the growing concern.
     </p>
     <p>
      ``You would think that people down here would be used to these storms already,'' he said. ``They act like it's all new, like they never heard of such a thing before.''
     </p>
     <p>
      But in this case, it may be true. This storm could be something entirely new.
     </p>
     <p>
      As if the threat of this hurricane was not enough bad news for Florida, another potentially dangerous storm, Hurricane Gert, seems to be taking roughly the same path as Floyd, just a few days behind.
     </p>
     <p>
      That storm, which developed into a full-fledged hurricane Monday, was expected to push through the Leeward Islands, Virgin Islands and Puerto Rico later this week, and _ if it stays on course _ eventually threaten Florida or the east coast. Though not as large as Floyd, Gert, the fifth hurricane of the season, was expected to pound through the Atlantic with winds well over 100 mph.
     </p>
     <p>
      For now, Floyd is trouble enough.
     </p>
     <p>
      On ritzy Worth Avenue in Palm Beach, Susan Bryden and six friends, visiting from Agawam, Mass., hurried through their shopping to make an evening flight home.
     </p>
     <p>
      ``We're leaving,'' said Ms. Bryden, as employees pulled shutters down on the windows of Saks Fifth Avenue and Ralph Lauren, ``and we're glad of it.''
     </p>
     <p>
      In Miami, the last cruise ship had lumbered out of the harbor by 6 p.m. Most workers had left downtown early. To the north, in Palm Beach, workers cleared the last chairs off the beaches.
     </p>
     <p>
      Cramer, the lifeguard, has seen this deceptive calm before.
     </p>
     <p>
      ``When you live here, you get used to the idea of hurricanes, but you respect them,'' he said. ``This one demands a lot of respect.''
     </p>
    </text>
    <trailer>
     NYT-09-13-99 1954EDT
    </trailer>
   </doc>
   